Hi, welcome back to Arya Nagarjuna.
If you remember in the last class,
we had gone through all the these trios.
We were trying to figure out
if you could have, for example,
the present and the future time
if you didn't have the past time.
So do the present and the future
only exist relative to the past?
And is that how the present
and the future exist,
through relation to the
past? Do the concepts
of past, present and future only exist
because of the comparison
between past, present and future?
And basically Nagarjuna says, "No."
Because, a comparison
between, for example,
present and future with past
would require that in some sense,
present and future would
have to make make contact
with past for there to
be a valid comparison.
There would have to be
some point of relationship.
And that, gets into touchy territory
because then something
which is present or future
would have to, would have to be touching
something which were past,
00:01:16,671 --> 00:01:19,807
and that's not viable.
It just doesn't work out.
Then the edge of the present
thing would have to be
the past also, to have a
relationship with the past.
There has to be a point of contact.
And you know, I think it's pretty natural
for us to believe that the
concept of present and future,
for example, relies upon
the concept of the past.
And how we establish
things as being future
or present or past in our own life
is done by comparison of the three.
And Nagarjuna is trying to point out
that that's untenable.
There cannot be a comparison
between past, present and future.
So the very concept of time
must be coming from someplace else.
Not by comparison, not
because of comparison.
And he said you can apply
that idea to other triads
or other groups of three.
For example, good karma,
bad karma, neutral karma.
He had some other examples, what's that?
Oh, best, worst and medium qualities.
What was the other one?
[Student] Numbers.
Oh yeah, even one two and
three depend on a comparison.
And we tend to inherently
believe that, for example,
that the difference between
one and two and three
depends on the comparison of the three.
And Nagarjuna is trying to say
that's not even possible.
So where does even the concept
of a progression of time,
how can time go from one
o'clock to two o'clock,
if it's not by comparison?
Where is it coming from?
And we'll get into it,
we'll get into the answer.
But first, he promised us two things:
he's going to examine concepts of time
from non-Buddhists schools
of Nagarjuna's time.
So it would be like us talking
about what modern physicists
think about time. In Nagarjuna's time,
if he wanted to have some juicy debate,
he would talk about the
idea of time, for example,
in the Sankhya Hindu school, or something.
And then by discussing their idea of time,
our idea of time would become more clear.
So first he promises a discussion of time
from other traditions.
And then he says, "Then let's
look at the concept of time
in other traditions of Buddhism,
other than Middle Way,"
and he's going to take
DNGOS SMRA BA, which means,
functionalist, which
means, people who think
that if something does something,
it should have some kind
of inherent existence.
If fire can be hot, then that heat
must somehow be inherent to fire.
Fires are never cold,
for example, freezing.
Hmm...so here we go.
This next verse, which is verse number five,
is going to present the
idea of another school,
another tradition of India
in the 2nd century A.D.
And here's the verse,
,MI GNAS DUS NI 'DZIN MI BYED,
,GANG ZHIG GZUNG BAR BYA BA'I DUS,
,GNAS PA YOD PA MA YIN PAS,
,MA BZUNG DUS NI JI LTAR GDAGS,
When you see GDAGS, G-D-A-G-S,
or any variation of it,
you automatically have to be suspicious.
What does it mean?
It means 'to attribute', or
'to call something something'.
Like when you say the
world exists just in words
or exists in names, the verb is GDAGS.
So anytime you see GDAGS,
usually at the end of a verse,
it means, how can you speak of
that, how can you apply that,
how can you refer to it
this way, meaning, falsely,
often times. All right.
So, 'GZHAN SDE NA RE'
Here's the actual debate (claps)
GZHAN SDE NA RE means 'other
traditions of ancient India',
maybe the Sankhya, the Hindu tradition.
They come to Nagarjuna and they say,
DUS RANG BZHIN KYIS YOD DE,
"Time exists in and of itself."
It is not a creation of our mind.
It not a creation of our karmic seeds.
It's not even a creation of
comparison between the times.
It exists in and of itself.
Time exists in a certain measurable way,
and it is not relative.
So, you can say science
before Einstein, right?
Newtonian mechanics.
Time has a certain definition.
RANG BZHIN KYIS YOD DE
Why?
SKAD CIG DANG THANG CIG DANG
YUD TZAM DANG NYIN MTSAN LA
SOGS PA TSAD DON GZHAN
DANG LTAN  PA'I PHYIR
Because time can be measured
in agreed upon units.
Time is measured in
seconds, minutes, hours,
days, season, years, decades, centuries.
We have created words and concepts
for the measurement of time.
So therefore, time does
have some existence
from its own side or it
could not have been named
millisecond, second, like that.
These are real measurements that you know,
an hour is 60 minutes. It's
not like 61, it's not like 59.
Therefore, it has some inherent existence.
An hour has to be 60 minutes.
It's an agreed upon convention.
Therefore, it has some
independent existence.
And here's Nagarjuna's response
DE MI RIGS TE
That's MI RIGS, that's
BS, that's all wrong. Why?
DUS NI SKAD CIG RE RE
BZHIN ZHIG NAS 'GRO BAS
If you think about it, time
passes in fleeting milliseconds.
ZHIG NAS 'GRO BAS THER ZUG MI GNAS
THER ZUG is a beautiful
word you should learn, Tim.
It means that 'it has no solid existence'.
THER ZUG is a beautiful,
poetic word that means
it has no solid existence.
THER ZUG TU MI GNAS PA'I PHYIR DANG
DUS LAS NGO BO THA DAD
PA'I SKAD CIG LA SOGS PA'I
SGO NAS 'DZIN PAR MI BYED PA'I PHYIR,
And you can't hold onto time.
You cannot grasp time,
you cannot catch time
and freeze it. Time is un-freezable.
Time cannot be, you cannot
grasp a certain millisecond
and say, "That's a millisecond."
It's too fleeting, it's too, un-THER ZUG
to even call it substantial.
PHYI MA GRUB STE,
DUS NI DE DAG CI RIGS LA BRTEN NAS
'DOGS PA TZAM YIN PA'I PHYIR
Units of time require
artificial measures.
They require artificial concepts.
You know, 60 minutes will be an hour.
And that's all made up in your mind.
You are taking things, all
units of time, up to centuries,
ultimately depend on milliseconds
or the shortest period of time.
And those are so fleeting that
you cannot grasp onto them.
So if you pile up ungraspable things,
you end up with just a
big ungraspable thing.
It's not like it becomes more
solid when you pile them up.
Because each one is undefinable.
Each one is uncatchable. You
can't catch a moment in time.
When you turn 69 you'll
understand it better.
(soft laughter)
Then the other guy says
a very beautiful thing
and these are all very thought-provoking,
and if you have time, these
are great for conversation
in a study group or for
meditation on your own.
And the one here he says,
KHO NA RE,
Now here's another school's
thought and they say,
DUS KYIS 'BYUNG BA SMIN PA
Time... how are we going to say this...
Time brings the elemental forces
of the universe to fruition.
of the the universe to fruition.
Therefore, it is solid.
Time's effect on gravity,
inertia, entropy,
basic electromagnetism,
time's effect on those
elemental forces of the universe
demonstrate that time must
have some solid existence
because it effects other things.
Time causes...this morning they announced
the astronomers for the first
time watched a star explode.
In present time, meaning
the light reached us,
they were able to observe a star exploding
for the first time, in real time.
I mean just a couple billion years behind.
(laughs)
What this guy says, what this
non-Buddhist guy says is,
"Look, if time had no substantial
existence, if it weren't solid,
then how can it cause a star to explode?"
A star explodes over
certain amount of time.
The time comes, it explodes,
it keeps exploding.
This requires time. In a way you can,
and it's going to come later,
time has a solid existence
because it is tetherable
to the phases of solid objects.
So you can say that
the phases of the moon,
you can assign them times.
And those are so solid,
that the times you assign to them:
full moon, half moon,
rising moon, dark moon,
those must have some
solid existences also.
The conventions that are
admittedly artificial of time,
if they are linked to a
real, natural occurrence,
like the phases of the moon,
then they take on some real existence.
They have some solid existence.
They're tied to a thing changing.
Then Nagarjuna won't have it.
And he says, "No no no,
you're trying to point out",
for example, a change in
the phase in the moon.
"You're trying to say that a certain time",
I don't know, "a half moon,
becomes a three-quarter moon
"or something, you're making
an artificial boundary
between a half moon and
a three-quarters moon."
But if you think about it, the
moment in which a half moon
changes to a three-quarter
moon is not something
you can freeze. You can't freeze it.
There's no point at which
it is purely half moon
and then in the next moment
it is purely three-quarters moon.
There's always some kind of overlap.
We call it phases of the moon.
It phases into the three-quarter moon.
There's no solid line where you can say,
it's now the three quarter moon.
You could say, you look it up online
and it says the moon's going
to change phase at 3:05 today.
But which 3:05? 3:05 and a
half? 3:05 and a quarter?
And then which 3:05 and a quarter?
The first part of 3:05 and a quarter
or the second part of 3:05 and a quarter?
And it's all...it is not something,
they keep using the word GZUNG.
Which means 'DZIN, which
means pointable to, grabbable.
Definable. Can't say this is the moment
at which the moon changed.
SKAD CIG DANG THANG CIG LA
And by the way,
in Buddhist philosophy, what's
the definition of existence?
[Student] That which is
perceived by valid perception
Yes.
TSAD MAS DMIGS PA YOD PA'I MTSAN NYID
Anything which is perceived
by an accurate perception exists.
And if it cannot be perceived
by an accurate perception
it doesn't exist.
What about a tree that falls in the forest
and nobody's there?
Somebody's always there
because the Buddha can see everything.
That's the classic answer.
But, TSAD MAS DMIGS PA means,
can an accurate perception
identify that moment?
And Nagarjuna says, "No.
Because identify means grasp."
Identify means grab onto a
certain point at which it is
the millisecond. But you
can't, there's no such thing.
Therefore, if you can't
grab, if you can't identify
the front end and back
end of a millisecond,
if you cannot identify the
front end and the back end
of a millisecond,
then because of the definition
of existence in Buddhism,
a millisecond cannot exist.
Because there is no pramana,
there is no accurate perception
which can catch it.
Maybe catch is a good verb here.
And that's a cool point.
That's a very cool point.
DE LTAR MA BZUNG BA'I DUS DE NI
SKAD CIG LA SOGS PA'I TSAD KYIS
JI LTAR GDAGS PAR YANG
MI NUS TE, MA 'BREL BA'I PHYIR
And if you can't even identify
a single millisecond of time,
then how are you going to describe
the difference between past
and present and future?
Because that hinges upon a
moment in which things change
to present from past, or
change from present to future.
If there's no point at which
past changes to present,
and if present never makes
contact with the past,
if there's no point of
contact which is observable,
then the divisions of time,
even into past, present,
and future are artificial
and arbitrary, and they
don't really exist,
from their own side. Cool.
I was trying to get a picture.
I really love finding these pictures.
It's like I spend all day
doing it. My wife wonders
what I'm doing.
I found a picture for
this one. I like this one.
Time has just flown...
Time flies out of the birdcage.
And you can't grab it
and say, "That's the
present or that's the past,
or that's when present
shifted to the past."
It's un-grabbable.
You grasp and it's gone already.
So I enjoy finding these pictures.
Now we reached the second
part. What was that?
We discussed other
traditions of ancient India.
Their idea of time, and
what did he promise us next?
Yes, how about some of our own groups,
who are not Middle Way?
What about the first three groups?
He's going to treat the
first three groups together.
Abhidharma, Sutrist and Mind Only,
which are called the functionalists.
They all believe that something is real
if it exhibits some kind of function.
So he says, "How do they think about time?
And can we poke holes in
their idea about time?"
Which is pretty much what
Nagarjuna spends his time doing,
if there were such a time.
So, here we go.
And by the way just for you guys,
the question of time is a
very unique circumstance
where the fourth school
and the first school agree,
and the second and third don't.
The idea that time is a functioning thing,
or the past especially, or the future.
The idea that the past does
something is not accepted
by school number two,
is not accepted by school number three,
but it is accepted by the
Abhidharma and Middle Way.
So it's a very rare case
where Abhidharma agrees
with Middle Way.
Now, and then what you have
to say in the next breath
always is, for different reasons.
Anyway, cancel that.
Here we go.
,GAL TE DUS NI DNGOS RTEN TE,
,DNGOS MED DUS NI GA LA YOD,
,DNGOS PO 'GA' YANG YOD MA YIN,
,DUS LTA YOD PAR GA LA 'GYUR,
And let's go to the commentary.
GAL TE RTAG PA'I DUS MED KYANG
SKAD CIG SOGS LA BRTEN NAS
THA DAD DU BZHAG PA'I DUS
NI NGO BOS YOD DO ZHE NA,
Somebody says, Look, I agree
there's no such thing as time
which is unchanging. That
far I agree with you.
But...
you can posit separate times
like past present and future
based on instances. You can
use the concept of a second
or an instant, and based on that,
you can artificially divide
the past from the present
and the present from the future.
If we all agree that we can use
an idea called a second or an hour,
then we can divide things.
This happened at 3 o'clock.
this happened at 4 o'clock.
We can, using artificial measurements
created by human beings,
we can describe time
this way. That's okay.
This is a lower three schools idea.
GAL TE GZUGS LA SOGS PA'I DNGOS PO
MED PA STE DE DAG LAS NGO BO
THA DAD PA'I DUS NI GA LA
YOD DE, DUS NI DNGOS PO LA
BRTEN NAS 'JOG PA'I PHYIR,
Then he says, "Does the
artificial units of time
which you agree to use, seconds, minutes?"
And this is cute, Nagarjuna
says, "Okay you want to make up
artificial measurements of time, right?"
And the guy says, "Yeah let's do that."
And like, "What do you want to use?"
He says, "Well, let's
use minutes and hours
and how about that?"
And this is another school and he says,
"Yeah, but I'll tell you something..."
Now, you guys got to cook it,
you guys got to see if you agree on it.
But Nagarjuna says, "Those
artificial units of time
that you just make up and we
all agree to use by convention
by mutual convention,
they exist only relative
to an observable entity."
You can only say minutes,
hours and days relative to
the moon phases changing or
the time it takes the sun
to come up and go down.
It's only by relative to
observable, actual entities,
that you could have an
artificial entity called hour
or day or month. Month as you know
is based on the phases of the moon.
Day is based on the phases of the sun.
And in Buddhist cosmology,
there are other measurements
of time based on the movement
of the constellations.
So in Buddhist cosmology, lunar, solar
and what is it, stellar,
measurement of time.
But, all three choices depend
on an outside physical entity.
The moon, the sun, the stars.
So Nagarjuna says, "Look, I agree,
you can make up units of
time. But don't you always
tie them to some
observable outside thing?"
Like a season is kind of tied
to the change in the weather,
and things like that.
So he says, "Don't they always?"
And then the other guys like,
"Yes, now that you mention it
the artificial units of
time which we have created
are created relative to,
they have to be linked
to, a changing DNGOS PO,
a functioning entity, on the outside."
DNGOS PO 'GA' YANG RANG BZHIN GYIS
YOD PA MIN NA DE LA BTAGS PA'I
DUS LTA
And then he says, "Well," says Nagarjuna,
"since the outside observable entities
that you want to link time
to don't exist from their own
side, then neither does the
time that is linked to them."
If the moon doesn't
exist from it's own side,
then the time, the artificial
convention called month
that you linked to that
thing, cannot be real.
Because the thing it is a
characteristic of is not real.
If the jar is not real,
then the green color
of the jar is not real.
If the moon is not real, then
the artificial measurement
month, based on the moon,
has to share that quality,
and it's not real either.
So that requires Nagarjuna to prove
that the moon is not real. (laughs)
So that's another story.
But he says, "Can we agree in theory,
that if the moon is not real,
then the artificial measurement
month, that you create
based upon the movement of
the moon is also not real?"
If you're creating a
convention that relies upon
another object's activity,
then if the other object's activity
is not coming from its own side,
if it's a fabrication of your mind,
due to your karmic seeds, then
can't we say time has to be that way also,
if it's a feature of that object?
If time is a feature of the moon
and the moon is not coming from the moon,
then can't we say that the
time that is based on the moon
has to be coming from you also?
And that it doesn't
actually have a measure,
an independent measure.
So it doesn't exist.
And moreover....(chuckles)
is there a point of contact
between the moon and month?
Months depend on the
movement of the moon. Yes.
Is there relationship
between them or not? Yes.
Is the idea month connected
to the moon? Yes.
Is there a point of contact? Yes,
otherwise month would be
connected to solar activity
or stellar activity. There
has to be a point of contact.
Well what part of the moon
touches what part of month, please?
Like that, it's impossible.
Month cannot be tied to the moon.
Because moon itself is
not tied to anything.
It's very beautiful.
You got to cook that one.
Then, by the way,
Can you see the sentence
DUS GSUM GYI RNAM GZHAG?
Do you see a sentence starting
Can you display that?
I don't know I didn't check the colophon,
which is the last few
sentences of the book
where he says, "I wrote this in my house,
in Choney Monastery, in 1747."
But I'm guessing it was late in his life.
He had a spurt of activity
late in his life, Choney Lama.
He wrote 200 books, I think half of them
were in the last ten years.
He went into retreat and
said, "I got to get this down!
I got to get this down!
They're going to mess it up after me."
I know the feeling.
So he's working like an insane man.
And he's cranking out these
books because he's thinking,
"no one's going to be
able to do it after me."
And then you get frustrating
sentences like this one, Tim.
DUS GSUM GYI RNAM GZHAG
This whole thing about
RNAM GZHAG means this whole presentation
on the idea of the three times.
BDAG GIS 'JUG PA'I RNAM BSHAD
I covered the whole
thing in my commentary to
DBU MA LA JUG PA, Madhyamakavatara,
"Entering the Middle Way" by Chandrakirti.
00:27:25,881 --> 00:27:28,423s
He says, "Hey, go and check
my commentary to Chadrakirti,
"not my commentary to Nagarjuna.
"I already wrote the whole thing,
"I already did the whole
thing. You want more on this?
"Go read my other book."
It's kind of frustrating when
you're translating this book.
I believe that morally
we will have to go get it,
snip it out, and put it in an appendix.
Then we'll have to translate it again
when we translate that book. But anyway...
So that's what I always do, personally I,
if he says, "I already covered
this is my other book,"
I feel obligated to go
find it, cut it out,
put it in the appendix and translate it.
We can only do that because
we have this amazing database,
created by Grandpa John.
Ot's the Grandpa #2.
Grandpa John Brady. Yay.
And it's so easy. It's so delightful to,
you know, in the old days it
would have taken many days.
But nowadays, you just sit
there, at my kitchen table,
and I say, "Hey database, tell
me what did Choney Lama say
about the three times in
that other commentary?"
And you can find it in about 30 seconds.
And you can cut it out
in another five seconds.
Then you have to translate.
That takes the same time.
But it's very cool.
It's unbelievably cool.
That's why these Mixed
Nuts books are so valuable,
in my opinion.
I have an example, I don't
know, I was trying to get cute,
which I'm always trying to do.
And there's a book and a clock.
And the idea is
only relative to an outside
object does time have meaning.
So how old is the book?
When was the book written?
How many years until the
Mixed Nuts translate it?
And Jasso becomes a Mixed Nut and translates?
How many years will pass and those,
the measurement of year only has meaning
relative to the physical book.
The book is defining time in a way.
The phases of the book's
existence are defining time.
When did John Brady input it?
When was it published?
When was it put online for free?
Those are all created measurements of time.
Part two.
Refer to the Elephant's Dance Sutra.
Any guesses what that means?
(student murmuring)
We said every chapter he's going to say,
"Hey, here's where
Nagarjuna got these ideas."
He's going to point back to the Buddha.
He says, "You want to know where Nagarjuna
"came up with all these time ideas?
"Go check out the Elephant's Dance Sutra."
That's Choney Llama.
And I like it because it
means Nagarjuna's ideas
are not just made up. The
ideas you are reading here,
from Nagarjuna, are his interpretation
of the original sutras. And
they always tie back to a sutra.
There might be a clue there
in which sutras are tied to
in working out the order
of chapters, but...
that's too much.
What's the third category
of this chapter going to be?
Last sentence.
The title of the chapter.
Here we get in Asian languages,
the name of the chapter comes at the end.
DUS BRTAG PA
kalā parīkṣā
(student murmurs)
An examination of time
or an investigation.
I almost like investigation,
because Nagarjuna
is kind of a very over,
what do you call it?
Over-achiever guy. He's
going to investigate.
He's not going to examine.
He's going to dig it out.
I called them examinations for couple years
and then I thought of investigation.
Drop the examinations. Let's
go to the investigations.
All right, next chapter.
Hmm....
What time, til 3:50 Tim?
15 more minutes.
Let's get here.
Artificially, oh wait, I
shouldn't give you that.
Anyway, Choney Llama attempts
to link this chapter
to the last chapter. Chapter 20 is called
"The Convergence of Causes and Conditions."
And, let me see, I think
there's a Sanskrit here
that's very useful.
Hmm....no not yet. Okay.
Anyway there's this
beautiful concept in...
(coughs) Sorry.
In this, this chapter called,
I think it's called 'sāmagryā'.
And you got to, I want
you to get the feeling
before you jump into this chapter.
I want you to get the feeling
of what he's talking about.
He's talking about the time being so ripe
that the thing has to happen.
All the conditions come together.
And you know, try to get your mind
on that particular instant.
All the necessary, the
e-book guy sent in his thing.
You know, the app guy
just finished the app.
Rosa finally has time to sit down
for the first half of
the day and work on it.
All these causes are going
to spit out a result.
So, Choney Lama, Nagarjuna,
they want you to
try to bring to mind that
special moment in time
when all the necessary
causes and conditions
have come together:
finance, concept, accounting
department, human resources,
blah blah blah. And now the
company can launch, you know?
Like it's that moment just
before the cafe opens:
the kitchen's done, the floor
is there, furniture is bought,
the signs are made,
the garden is landscaped,
the toilet is there. (laughs)
And boom, it's just about to open.
He wants you to think about that moment.
And he calls the chapter,
the moment when all the
stuff came together.
And it's the moment just
before the result pops up.
All right, so get your mind on that.
Now, here's the structure
of the whole chapter.
You ready? Here's the
structure of the whole chapter.
Try to put your mind
on that special moment
when everything you need
for something to happen,
like the opening of the cafe,
has finally come together.
Everything's finished: furniture's bought,
we found workers, all the
stuff has come together.
Put your mind on that moment
called the...what did I
call it the other day?
The consummate completion.
The consummate...coming together...consummate convergence.
All the causes, all the necessary stuff
that needed to happen has happened.
Now, my question to you.
Does that happen before
the result comes out?
Does that happen as the result comes out?
Or does it happen strangely
after the result comes out?
Do you open the cafe,
after everything's ready?
Or do you open the cafe just
before everything's ready?
Or do you open the cafe
as everything's ready?
I think naturally, what would we say?
What do you guys think?
(student replies): After everything's ready.
Yes, normally you'd say, "Geshe-la,
get the money together
before you open it."
Don't open it and then look for the money,
nothing like that.
By the way there is money.
But I took the Doctor
Chen's advice long ago.
30 years ago. I asked this
great Chinese philanthropist,
"What's your secret for doing projects?"
He says, "I start the project, Michael,
after I have the money." (laughs)
And I'll never forget it.
I always...isn't that the story here?
Start the cafe, open the cafe, after you got
the, what do you call that..
capital together and don't mess with it.
But, Nagarjuna requires us to consider
the other two possibilities.
Could it be possible that
the result is happening
as the cause and the
conditions come together?
Or could there be some angle
where the causes and conditions
have only come together
after the result has come?
Could there be some way
of looking at it that way?
Jasso's already there.
Shh..don't tell on me...I can
sense you're already there.
Here we go...
Now a question. Put your mind on this.
When you get all the money for the cafe
and all the equipment
and all the employees,
and blah blah blah...permits.
God bless permits.
When they're all together,
is the opening of the cafe present or not?
In the convening of the
necessary causes and conditions
is the opening in it?
In the convention. Convening.
Is the opening present in the
final collection of all the
things you need to open?
Is the opening there or not?
I think conventionally
you'd say, "Not yet."
Or, "It's just about to
be there," or something.
The opening's not there,
but everything you need
for the opening is there.
But Geshe-la, technically, the opening
is not one of the
conditions for the opening.
So it's not there yet.
Okay, got it?
Like you can have a seed and
a gardener and a sunlight
and fertilizer, but there's no flower yet.
Is the flower there when the
gardener's planting the seed?
And that's what...we're going
to examine, the possibility.
So here we go.
Okay, good.
Then he says, what time
am I stopping Tim? 3 5 5.
(Tim murmurs)
How much? 10 minutes.
6 minutes, okay I'm just
trying to keep track.
,GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS KYI,
,TSOGS PA NYID LAS SKYE 'GYUR ZHING,
,TSOGS LA 'BRAS BU YOD NA NI,
,JI LTAR TSOGS PA NYID LAS SKYE,
If the opening of the cafe is present
in the final convening of
all the causes and conditions
then why the hell do we
have to open the cafe?
(students laugh)
It's already open.
It's that cute (laughs), it's very cute.
Then why do you have to open the cafe?
It's already open.
If the opening of the cafe is present
in the convening of
the final requirements,
then we don't have to
open the cafe, all right?
,GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS KYI,
,TSOGS PA NYID LAS SKYE 'GYUR ZHING,
,TSOGS LA 'BRAS BU MED NA NI,
,JI LTAR TSOGS PA NYID LAS SKYE,
But if the opening of the
cafe is not somehow present
within this particular
causes and conditions,
then how could a cafe open?
Then you would just open
a bookstore or something.
See, why should a cafe
open when all the causes
and conditions to open a cafe are present?
If the opening of the cafe
is somehow not present
in that final convening of
the causes and conditions,
because if the opening of
the cafe was not present,
in some degree, during the final convening
of the causes and conditions
for the opening of the cafe,
then when the causes and
conditions finally did their thing,
it should pop out a
rabbit's turd or something.
See what I mean?
Why wouldn't anything pop out?
I'll say it again.
If the opening of the
cafe is not in some degree
present within the final
moment of the convening
of all the necessities
for the cafe to open,
then when they do convene,
why should they open a cafe?
Why shouldn't they open a
rabbit's turd or something?
I mean, what's...because
there's no relationship.
There's no necessary relationship.
There's no more reason
why a cafe should pop out
than a rabbit's turd, if the
cafe is not in some degree
present in the final convening
of causes and conditions.
Okay, got it?
Or at least, I think
in English we would say
the potential is somehow there.
There's more potential
for a cafe to pop out
then rabbit turd to pop out.
Something like that.
But it's...here we go, okay?
Here comes the question.
Actually I just covered it.
TSOGS LA 'BRAS BU RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD NA
Yeah, if the result of the cafe popping out
were somehow present the moment before,
during the time of the final convening
of all the things you
need to open the cafe,
then there wouldn't be
a need to open the cafe,
because it would already be open.
And it would be redundant.
He keeps using the word redundant.
There wouldn't be any
point to opening the cafe
a second time, a millisecond later.
Here's a picture. I had
trouble with the picture.
I couldn't find a picture that
you didn't have to explain.
But somehow, if the watermelon
were already present
in the seeds and being together and then,
why would you have to plant the seeds.
There wouldn't be any point to it.
I'm calling this watermelon,
the watermelon which came from
the seeds that you see now.
If the watermelon were already present
in the time of its seeds,
then why would the seeds
have to do anything?
Got it?
All right, hmm...
And suppose the result is not somehow
present even as a potential in the final
convening of the causes and conditions,
then it could never grow.
And I don't know, as
desperate I got an apple here.
You can see the apple.
It's metal apple. So it
didn't grow from anything.
Got it? Makes sense?
If the result is not
present in the convening
of the causes and conditions,
then why would it ever create that cause?
If it's not somehow connected to the final
coming together of the
causes and conditions,
which means it pre-exists,
then why would an apple come out?
Why wouldn't something else come out?
And there's another deep problem there.
Nagarjuna keeps coming
back to the idea that
if things are not coming from you,
if things are coming from their own side,
they cannot change. They
have no reason to change.
(coughs) I'll say it again.
Nagarjuna keeps coming back to this theme,
which you guys can chew on, that
if the cause is somehow
not present in the causes,
if the result were self-existent,
then it couldn't change.
If something is self-existent,
it will always have to be the same.
Because it doesn't depend on
its existence on other things.
If the jar were self-existent,
then it would never break,
or it could never be made because
it just existed by itself.
It didn't exist because of a factory
or didn't break because I dropped it.
It would just be all the time the same.
If it does change, it's not self-existent.
That's all.
Let me see if that's a good place to stop.
That's a great place to stop.
Okay, Uncle Tim?
And, we'll do one more class.
Thank you guys.